Coffee. Coffeeans.
（みどり）
コーヒー… コーヒー星人
黒くてコーヒーの中に住んでいる
They're black and live inside coffee.
They argue with her mother, who accidentally poured mentsuyu sauce instead of coffee.
コーヒーと めんつゆを間違えて
お母さんとケンカ
コーヒー経済評論家
Coffee business analyst...
Focusing on a locked room murder over good coffee...
あっ 集中して
コーヒー飲んでる間に密室殺人
Accidentally spills coffee
on another... Office romance...
コーヒーかけられてシミ
オフィスラブ
A single black pearl inside a coffee bean...
コーヒー豆の中に
１粒だけ黒真珠 オニキス 密輸
Onyx...
Smuggling...
（池谷(いけたに)）
ハァ ハァ ハァ ハァ
（矢野(やの)）おはようございます
（池谷）うわっ！
Good morning! Have you finished any cuts from episode 5?
５話の上がり
いかがでしょうか？
いや 違うの　これは あのね…
This isn't what it looks like. I just...
11話の絵コンテ打ちも
ありますからね
And don't forget about the
episode 11 storyboard meeting.
I'll Try Even Hawker!
The problem is the 13th episode, the finale.
（舞茸(まいたけ)）
問題は最終13話でしょ
I know.
（木下(きのした)）
だよね～
I sent the manuscript for episode 12
in for checks the other day.
ラス前の12話は
とりあえず
原稿チェックに回したけどさ
原作は
この先の展開どうなるって？
Do we know how the source is going to continue?
Sorry, but no.
（あおい）
すみません
Watanabe-san has been asking about it.
渡辺(わたなべ)さん通じて
聞いてもらってるんですけど…
All I got was a, "We'll leave it to you."
（渡辺）
お任せしますってだけですね
（葛城(かつらぎ)）
原作者も まだ先が
見えてないんじゃないの？
Maybe the author hasn't decided how it'll go yet himself.
That's not an issue for his work, but it's a real problem for us.
原作は
それでいいかもしれませんが
アニメは そうはいきませんよ
Don't worry too much. Just have some ice cream!
まあまあ
アイスでも食べて 舞茸さん
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
（舞茸）
それはクールダウン
しろってことですか？
Are you saying I should cool my temper?
（木下）
うん？　いや～ おいしいから
Nah, just that it's yummy.
俺のおすすめは高原ミルク味
I recommend the highland milk flavor.
う～ん まあ食べますけど
Fine, I'll have one.
The issue still remains about how to proceed. What's the schedule?
…で 実際問題
どう進めればいいの？
スケジュールは？
９月中旬で決定稿　10月なかには
絵コンテアップのつもりです
Final script by mid-September,
and storyboards done by mid-October.
えっ 無理だよ それ！
あと２週間じゃん
You're asking the impossible!
That only gives us two weeks!
I'm sorry, but we can't push it back any further.
すみません
でも もうホントにギリギリで
And that only gives us two months from storyboards to finished product.
これでも絵コンテアップから
納品２か月しかありません
…つか 絵コンテには
１か月時間 取るのに
So storyboards get a whole month, and I only get a couple of weeks?
僕にはそれだけって…
舞茸さんだから
ついつい頼っちゃうんですよ
That's because we believe in you, Maitake-san.
We're really counting on you.
お願いしますよ～
You need to work faster, director!
監督が早く上げてくださいよ
I'll try!
（木下）頑張る！
（舞茸）軽いな～ このデブ
You sound so relaxed, fatty.
（木下）
今 デブって言った？
Did you just call me fat?
Maybe I did, maybe I didn't. I forget.
言ったような気がするけど
覚えてません
I even lost 500...
（木下）
これでも500減らしたのに～
What, grams? That's in the margin of error!
グラムでしょ？
んなの誤差ですよ 誤差
息吐いて量れば
それくらい減りますから
You can lose that much just by exhaling.
Really? I was having this to reward myself.
えっ！　自分へのご褒美だと思って
食べてたのに
どこのＯＬですか
What are you, an office lady?
自分への罰は
何も下さないくせに
And where are your punishments for failing?
ふんっ
Anyway, about the final episode...
それで最終回なんですけども
おっ 話 戻した
Finally getting back on topic.
I'd like to run with what the editor said and get the scenario done ASAP.
編集さんのお任せしますという
言葉を信じて
シナリオを早く形にしたいです
I understand that, but...
それはそうなんだけどさ～
Um, where we are in the plot, Aria can't fly.
（みどり）
えっと 今 ありあが
飛べなくなってるじゃないですか
But in the end, she should be flying again, right?
最終的には
飛ばないといけないんですよね？
The story wouldn't wrap up otherwise.
まあ 話としては
そうしないと終わらないしね
いっそのこと―
Ending it without her ever flying again...
飛ばないまま終わり…
（葛城）ええ！
What?!
（みどり）イヤです！
（あおい）ダメです！
Not a chance!
You'll definitely want to make her fly again when you work on the storyboards!
絶対 絵コンテ描いてるうちに
やっぱり飛ばしたいって
なるに決まってます！
In the source, she hasn't flown for half a year at this point.
原作は ありあが飛ばなくなって
もう半年だっけ？
Yes. The other girls are having a tough fight against the Builders.
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
今はキャシーたちの
対ビルダー苦闘編みたいに
なってますね
That'll definitely take a while.
（舞茸）
長引きそうだな～
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
漫画はいいよね～ 尺なんて
いくらでも調整できるから
Manga is so easy.
You never have to worry about the length.
Hey, this is your problem too, you know.
（舞茸）
ひと事みたいに
言わないでくださいよ
I already know how it's gonna end.
やることは決まってるんだよ
Aria flies again to a triumphant victory!
ありあが再び飛ぶ！
勝利を収めるビクトリー！
The war isn't over yet though.
そして戦いは続く
Easier said than done.
ホント簡単に言いますね
いやいやいや 難しいことほど
I think it's best to put complicated things like this as simply as possible.
ひと言で言ったほうが
いいかと思って
The question is what could make her fly again, right?
どうやったら ありあが
もっかい飛ぶ気になるかですよね
Exactly right.
それなんだよ
She lost her family, and flying was all that gave her life meaning, right?
ありあはさ 家族を失って
飛ぶことだけが
存在意義だった子だろ
But now she says she'll never fly again.
なのに飛ぶことをやめたってのは…
In the previous episode, I could build up to it and have her say, "I won't fly. I quit."
前話数のヒキは“もう飛ばない
降りる”でよかったけど
But what comes after that? What do we do, Dr. Diesel?
その次がさ～
どうするよ ディーゼルさん
I don't know.
（みどり）いや 分かんないです
（舞茸）おい～
Come on...
I wouldn't quit.
私なら絶対 降りないです
Especially if it meant everything to me.
それ取ったら自分には何もないって
分かってるんなら なおさら
だから どうやったら
もっかい飛ぶようになるのか
So I have no idea what could make her fly again.
分かんないです
飛ぶ意味って なんなのかな？
I wonder what it means to be a pilot.
What it means? Dunno.
意味っすか？　なんだろう？
It seems complicated.
Not that I've ever tried myself.
（あおい）
難しいよね　飛んだことないけど
Isn't that kind of like asking us why we like making anime?
（舞茸）
それは我々にとって
なんでアニメを作るのか
…みたいなことじゃないの？
Oh! Now I understand!
あっ そうか
それだったら分かります
（舞茸）
えっ 宮森(みやもり)さんは
So what is it that drives you, Miyamori-san?
なんで作ってんの？
I only meant that I got the premise and all.
いや 質問の意味が
分かるってだけで
I'm not sure I know my own reason.
作る意味とか 全然
Right...
だよね～
That's not a question most people could easily answer.
（舞茸）
普通 なんでアニメを作るのかって
言われてもね～
Why are you making anime, director?
（あおい）
監督は なんでアニメ
作ってるんですか？
Huh? Me?
うん？　俺？　う～ん
Uh... Just 'cause?
（木下）なんとなく
（一同）はあ？
But I can't up and quit now.
でも やめられないんだよね
I wonder why.
なんでかな～
（笑い声）
舞茸さんは どうなんですか？
What about you, Maitake-san?
I never gave much thought to this kind of existential question.
僕だって
意味とか大層なこと考えてないよ
I just focused on each deadline,
and before I knew it decades had passed.
あしたの締め切りだけこなしてたら
何十年もたっちゃっただけでさ
Could say it's to make a living.
まっ 言っちまうと
生活のためですな
So any other job would be fine?
（舞茸）
それなら別の仕事でもいいじゃない
I suppose. I wonder why I ended up with this job.
そうなんですよね～
なんで こんな仕事に
就いちゃったかな～
“こんな”って
It's not that bad!
It's all about the excitement for me.
（葛城）僕は刺激かな
（あおい）刺激？
Excitement?
Excite the viewers,
見る人に刺激を与えたいし
作ることで自分も刺激を受けたい
and enjoy the excitement of making it.
Where'd you steal that line from? A book?
なんすか
柄でもないキレイ事発言
Aren't you just trying to hit the jackpot?
ホントは“ひと山当てたい”
じゃないんですか？
そりゃ当てたいよ！
Sure, I'd love that!
It'd be great, but I'd lose interest if it was only about money.
当てたいけどさ
それだけじゃ つまんないだろ
アニメなんて
株より投資効率 悪いのに
You make more investing in stocks than in anime.
Not all good shows are successful.
These days there are more bad shows topping the charts.
いい作品が当たるとは限らないし
その逆も またしかり
So true.
ホントだよね～
I'd love to make a good show that's also successful. Slim chance, though.
それこそ いい作品で
当てたいんだけど
両立は なかなかね～
Wow, you all had such different answers!
みんなバラバラなんですね
面白いです
Pretty interesting!
I'll try outlining a plot.
（舞茸）
じゃ とりあえず
プロット立ててみますけど…
Thank you.
（葛城）
お願いします
I'm not too confident this time, though.
自信ないっすよ 今回ばかりは
大丈夫ですよ　期待してますから！
You'll be fine! We're counting on you.
What he said!
このとおり！
Much easier said than done.
ホント軽いな～
I'm really sorry, Maitake-san.
舞茸さん 本当にすみません
It's fine.
（舞茸）
しかたない
宮森ちゃんが悪いわけじゃないし
It's not your fault, Miyamori-chan.
そんなことより
目先の締め切り 締め切り
But I've got a deadline to worry about now.
（みどり）あっ あっ 師匠！
（あおい）うん？
Ah, master!
I told you not to call me that.
（舞茸）
師匠じゃねえっつったろ
I did the coffee exercise.
コーヒーの課題 やってきました
Do a quarrel next.
Under five pages or a thousand words.
んじゃさ 次に“ケンカ”
ペラ５枚 1,000文字以内で
A quarrel?
ケンカ… ですか？
Use any premise and characters you'd like.
原因 人物 なんでもいい
とにかくケンカについてワンシーン
Just write a scene about some guys arguing.
了解です！
Roger!
Rii-chan, what was that all about?
（あおい）
りーちゃん 何 さっきの？
It's kinda like writer training.
う～んと ライター修業みたいな
Coffee and quarrels?
コーヒーとケンカが？
He told me to think up 20 situations involving coffee.
コーヒーのあるシチュエーションを
20個 考えろって言われて
Coffeeans.
“コーヒー星人 ふだんは液体
ゼリーにもなり胃袋から侵略”
They are normally liquid but can turn gelatinous and invade from within the stomach.
Wait, so you're Maitake-san's apprentice now?
もしかして
舞茸さんの弟子になったの？
いや 断られたっす
弟子は取らないって
No, he turned me down when I asked.
He doesn't take apprentices.
No means no. Give MiG a break!
（舞茸）
だからもファントムもない！
Please! I'll try even Hawker!
（みどり）
頑張りマスタング！
You could be my Messer!
どうかお願いしメッサー
（舞茸）
シュミットかよ
I'm no Schmitt.
Chuo Line       For Tachikawa, Hachioji, Takao
For Kichijoji, Shinjuku, Tokyo        Chuo Line
Rapid
Tokyo
JAS perfect!
スホーイ スホーイ
ディーゼルさんに言っとく
僕は 弟子は取らない
Let me be clear, Dr. Diesel.
I do not take apprentices.
However...
取らないが…
“課題なら出してやる”って
言われて
He told me he'd give me assignments anyway.
へえ～ よかったね りーちゃん
第一歩だね
That's great!
It's the first step!
Or second.
いや 第三歩 第四歩くらいかも！
Or third. Or maybe fourth?
I've only just started.
これからっすけど
You know how we talked about why we make anime?
さっき なんでアニメを作るのか
って話になったじゃないですか
For me, it's because I need stories.
（みどり）
自分には やっぱり物語が
必要なんだなって思うです
You need stories?
必要？　物語が？
I know that some people don't need stories.
必要のない人がいるってことは
分かるんす
Like my parents.
（みどり）うちの親みたいに
（あおい）あ…
But I want to hear and write stories!
でも 私は
物語が見たいし作りたい！
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing  ep 4
（安藤(あんどう)）
やっぱ“好きだから”
以外にないですね
The best reason I can give you is, "because I like it."
You mean you like BL.
（太郎(たろう)）
ＢＬが好きってだけだろ？
Derivative works demonstrate an understanding of
the original story and love for the characters.
二次創作って
作品に対する理解と
キャラに対する共感の
塊ですからね
That's critical for production staff too.
制作に必要なスキルだと思います
自己評価 高すぎ
Sounds like you're putting on airs.
Why are you making anime then, Takanashi-san?
（安藤）
高梨(たかなし)さんは なんで
アニメ作ってらっしゃるんですか？
Isn't that obvious?
あ？　そんなの決まってるだろ！
To make the great Japanimation...
世界に冠たる
ジャパニメーションの… えっと
realize its potential... as content business...
コンテンツビジネスとしての
ポテンシャルをだな…
You're just spewing buzzwords.
（安藤）適当 言ってますよね？
（太郎）ぐはっ
だって面白いじゃないですか
Isn't it fun?
Is that it?
（木下）
それだけ？
This field is full of weirdos.
変な人間ばっかりですよね
この業界
Lazy. Childish. Hopeless pieces of useless trash.
だらしない 大人げない
どうしようもないカスゴミ クズ
But I guess it's fine, since they're all nice people on the inside.
だけど基本的に みんな善人だから
いいかって…
（山田(やまだ)）
俺がアニメを作るのは
I guess I'm making anime to prove I exist. Leave my mark.
自分が ここにいるってのを
確認するためかな
Wow!
（みどり）スホ～イ
（円(まどか)）うへ～ 壮大だな
That's deep.
Isn't that what life's all about?
生きるって そういうことだろ？
だから俺は「ぷる天」も
なかったことにしないよ
That's why I won't deny that BoingPara happened.
It's a part of who I am now.
あれも俺という人間の一部だから
So you fully accept yourself, huh?
山田さんは
自分 全肯定の人なんですね
I try not to be arrogant,
増長はよくないけど
but if you don't believe in yourself, who will?
自分くらい
自分を信じてやんないとさ
I wonder what my reason is.
（円）
俺は なんだろうな
Maybe I'm making this show because I'm looking forward to the next one.
次の作品を作りたいから
今の作品を作ってんのかな
Right hand
Make it more feminine
Make her look this way
Thank you
What about you, Satou-san?
Do you have a reason?
（あおい）佐藤(さとう)さんは？
（佐藤）あっ
理由とかってある？
I haven't thought much about it,
（佐藤）
えっ 深く考えたこと
なかったですけど
but I guess it's also because I just like it.
私もやっぱり
好きだからかもしれません
えっ どれ？　何萌(も)えですか？
Really? What about it turns you on?
う～ん
ではなくて 会社の雰囲気が
I meant the work atmosphere.
こうやって一丸となって
完成を目指す感じが
The way we work as one to finish something.
一丸かな～
Are we really as one?
At JusOn we'd have various goals, like satisfying the customers,
ジャスオンみたいな会社だと
お客様を満足させるとか
利益を上げるとか
maximizing profits, or improving efficiency.
効率をよくするとか
目的が いくつもあるんですね
その点アニメは とにかく
完成させるという大目標があって
In contrast, everyone here has the
overall goal of finishing the product.
I think it's great how we all work towards that.
それに まい進する状況が
すごく潔いと思います
Ah, sorry.
あっ すいません
Must be nice to be a girl.
（平岡）いいよな 女は
（みどり）えっ？
おっさんに ちょっといい顔すりゃ
なんでもやらせてもらえるし
Just flash a smile at some old fart and they'll let you do whatever.
Everything's handed to you.
なんでも思いどおりになるもんな
Have you any idea how many people work
themselves to the bone but never get a chance?
ちゃんと仕事してんのに
チャンスもらえない人間が
どれだけいると思ってんだ
Don't take this job lightly, newbie!
素人が この仕事
ナメてんじゃねえぞ
Must be nice to be a girl...
“いいよな 女は
ナメてんじゃねえぞ”
Don't take this job lightly...
Are you nuts or what? Who's taking it lightly?
（みどり）
“バカじゃないの？”
“ナメるとか
ナメてないとか何？”
You think a few mean words will scare me off?
“ドス利かせればビビると
思ってる？”
See? This is why I hate girls who aren't cute.
“これだよ これだから
かわいげのない女はイヤなんだよ”
Girls should just smile and nod to everything.
“女は はいはい言ってれば
いいんだよ”
“ウフフ 宝くじで当たった６億円
どうやって使おう”
How should I spend the 600 million I won in the lottery now?
Should I throw it all from the roof of a building?
“いっそビルの上から
まいてやろうかねえ”
“嫁のほえ面が楽しみだ”
Can't wait to see my daughter-in-law bawling.
It's surprisingly hard to feign sleep.
“タヌキ寝入りって
意外と難しいんだな”
I just have to give this data to the
transporter getting on at the next stop.
“次の駅で乗り込んでくる運び屋に
このデータを…”
Yup. I've perfected my act.
“よし 今の演技 完璧だぜ”
I guess it has to come down to this.
やっぱり こうなるよね　うん…
Yeah, I think it should be like this.
このとおりだと思います
（舞茸）ホントに？
（木下）ホントです
Really?
Really.
Um...
（あおい）あの…
（木下･舞茸）うん？
I agree with what it'll all
come down to and how it should go,
私も“こうなるよね”
“このとおりだと思います”
なんですけど
but filling the end of part A and all of part B
with action might be pushing it schedule-wise.
Ａパートの終わりからＢパート
まるまるアクションなのは
スケジュール的に重すぎませんか？
It's unavoidable with the plot being what it is.
まあ でも作劇上しかたないよね
Miyamori, send the plot to Nighthawk Publishing.
宮森 プロット
夜鷹(よたか)書房さんにメールしといて
（あおい）
あっ はい
Okay.
So I can start writing the scenario, right?
んじゃ シナリオ書き始めて
いいってことだね？
It's in your good hands.
（木下）お願いします
（一同）お願いします
Please do!
Thank you.
（みどり）
お疲れさまでした
You've had perfect attendance so far.
You giving up on that?
お？　皆勤賞だったのに
とうとう脱落か？
That's not it! I did it!
や… やってあります
やってきました！
Then what? You lost confidence?
なんだよ 自信ないとか言う気か？
Already? Come on.
（舞茸）100年 早いぞ
（みどり）うう…
A Situation with a Quarrel
Man "Must be nice to be a girl. Don't take this lightly!"
Woman "Are you nuts or what?
What about taking it lightly or not?"
It's pretty raw.
（舞茸）なんか生々しいね
（みどり）うっ
Master!
師匠！
I'm not your master, but what?
師匠じゃないけど 何？
I've never once considered you a man!
私 師匠が男だとか
思ったことありませんから！
Huh?
Gender has nothing to do with why I wanted to work with you.
男とか女とか そういうので
仕事したいと思ったわけじゃないし
I'm not taking anything lightly because of my gender either!
今も男とか女とか
ナメてません！
（舞茸）
はあ？　何言ってんの お前
誰かに妙なこと言われたか？
What are you going on about?
Did someone say something weird to you?
Work is work.
仕事は仕事
If you get that, then you're good to go.
そんなの自分で
分かってりゃいいんだよ
As for this, it needs a retake.
あと これはリテーク
It's not interesting to read your experience as-is.
実体験をまんま読まされても
面白くない！
えっ もう一声
お願いできますか 師匠！
Can I ask you one more thing, master?
（舞茸）
師匠じゃねえっつうの！
なんだよ もう一声って
I'm not your master. What is it?
Madoka-san, are those episode 7 layout checks done yet or what?
（平岡）
円さ～ん
７話のレイアウトチェック
どうなってます？
Can't you see I'm working on it?
見りゃあ分かるだろ～
やってるよ
I need to prioritize the keyframe checks for episode 3, since cutting is tomorrow.
カッティング前日の
３話原画チェックと
並行なんかできねえよ
すぐ原画に戻したいんですけど
I wanna hand them over to the keyframers.
ああ？　昨晩いきなり
カットの山 持ってきて
What? You bring me a huge pile of cuts last night and now you've got the nerve to ask that?
その言い方はないだろ
あ～ すいませんね
なるべく早く急いでくださいよ
Yeah, sorry. Just get it done as soon as possible, please.
Do I look like I'm slacking to you?
お～い 俺が
サボってるように見える？
Don't get so worked up.
つっかからないでくださいよ～
I'm not here for you to take your stress out on.
俺に八つ当たりされても困ります
Retake again.
再リテーク
（平岡）
はあ？　再リ？
Again?!
ED
Director
Memos are inside. Sorry and thank you.
ED R2 draw it properly please
勘弁してくださいよ
Give me a break!
Madoka-san, you know you're making more work for yourself asking for retakes on everything, right?
円さん リテーク乱発して 自分の首
絞めてるって分かってます？
They're gonna quit on us if they read that.
こんな言い方 降りられますよ
降りて結構
むしろ降りてくれよ
I wouldn't mind that either.
On the contrary, I'd be happy.
Huh?
（平岡）ああ？
（円）降ろせって言ってんだよ
I'm telling you to find someone else.
I don't need this guy.
こいつ いらねえわ
What are you trying to say?
それ どういう意味っすか？
All those animators you introduced like you were the king of the office.
お前がドヤ顔で連れてきた
アニメーターな
全員 まるまる使えねえんだよ！
They're all completely useless, every last one!
They just scribble something and call it a day!
どいつもこいつも
落書き出してきやがって
Then you find someone better!
じゃあ 自分で連れてこいよ！
職務放棄してんじゃねえよ！
How about you do your god damn job?!
You can't do anything, can you?
（円）ホント お前 何もないよな
（平岡）はあ？
Why are you even working here?
なんのために制作やってんだよ！
You always lurk around looking bored, then slack around and do sloppy work!
いっつも いっつも
つまんなそうな顔で
雑な仕事で手ぇ抜いて！
You proudly claim you've done this and that,
あれやった これやったって
自慢するけどよ
お前の仕事っぷりで
キャリアんなると思ってんのか？
but if you think you'll get anywhere with that attitude, you're sadly mistaken!
ならねえよ！　笑わせんじゃねえ！
Who're you even kidding?!
はあ！　演出が進行に
責任転嫁してんじゃねえよ！
Don't try to put this on me, episode director!
Quit acting like you're my boss or something!
We're the same age!
上から目線で空威張りすんな！
同い年だろうが！
（円）年は関係ねえ！
（あおい）どうしたんですか？
That's completely irrelevant!
What's going on?
At this rate it'd be better to have Tarou draw these!
Did you call me?
（太郎）呼びました？
（矢野）バカ！　止めろ 太郎！
You idiot! Stop, Tarou!
（太郎）えっ うわ～！
（興津(おきつ)）ふっ！
I consider violence outright disgusting.
（興津）
私がサイテーだと思うのは
暴力行為です
Whether it is direct or not,
it is unacceptable and will not be tolerated.
それが直接であれ間接であれ
暴力は絶対に許されませんし
許しません
Let's all apologize to Okitsu-san, okay? Right?
謝ろう！
みんなで興津さんに謝ろう！
ねっ ごめんなさい 興津さん
We're terribly sorry, Okitsu-san!
When I was young, spats like that were everyday occurrences.
（丸川(まるかわ)）
僕が若い頃は こういう荒事は
日常茶飯事だったけど
It's unusual these days though.
今どきは珍しいね
I don't know the proper way to drink tea.
お茶の飲み方とか
分かんないんですけど
いいの いいの 適当で
Don't worry about it.
He hit the bull's eye, didn't he?
（丸川）図星だったんだよね？
（平岡）うっ
That's why you got so upset.
だから腹を立てた
You wouldn't have cared if he said something totally off the mark.
見当違いのことを言われたんなら
どうでもいいはずだよ
はあ～ もういいっすか？
Can I go now?
（丸川）あしたから来ない？
（平岡）あっ…
So you won't be coming in anymore?
I hope that's not the case, Hiraoka-kun.
な～んてことはないよね？
平岡君
あっ… あ～ 来た来た ケンカ番長
やるじゃん 大(だい)ちゃん！
Here comes the great fighter! You ain't half-bad, Dai-chan!
Bang! It was amazing!
バ～ンってすごかったな～
バ～ン！　ドカ～ン！　ステキ～
Bam! Shabang!
Just wonderful!
Tarou, you can't be serious.
（矢野）太郎 お前な～
（佐藤･安藤）ハハハ…
Hiraoka-san, did you get hurt?
（あおい）
平岡さん ケガなかったですか？
Nope.
別に
Madoka-san.
円さん
I'm sorry.
すみませんでした
うん こっちも悪かった
I'm sorry too.
Who'd even notice it?
Please don't just copy all the action
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
Ep 7
Animator
Miura
ED
Director
AD
CAD
Master
LF
Effect
（平岡）
別に分かんねえだろ
こんなもん
If the art's fine above the neck,
the viewers will be happy with it.
首から上が ちゃんと描けてれば
客は満足なんだよ
It doesn't matter how much effort the animators put in.
いくら作画が気合い入れようが
入れまいが変わらねえっつうの
Wro—
（久乃木(くのぎ)）ち！
（平岡）あっ
Wro? At least finish a word!
“ち”？
なんだよ 最後まで言えよ
Great! I can go to work tomorrow.
（絵麻(えま)）
よかった～ あしたは会社 行ける
Yes?
（絵麻）はい あっ…
（久乃木）あっ！
Kunogi-san? How did you know where I live?
（絵麻）
久乃木さん
なんで うちが分かったの？
Did you ask Aoi-chan?
あ～ もしかして
おいちゃんから聞いた？
うん　めい…
Dis?
You're not disturbing me.
迷惑じゃないけど
どうしたの？
What's wrong?
あっ 久乃木さん！
Kunogi-san!
フフッ ちょっと寄ってく？
私も もう風邪 治りかけだし
Would you like to come inside?
My cold's gotten better.
Wro?
（久乃木）ち！
（絵麻）うん 違うよね
Yes, I think he's wrong.
People can definitely see the difference.
見てる人に
分かんないなんてことはないよ
Call me naive,
（絵麻）
キレイ事かもしれないけど
熱意とか やる気とか努力とか
but I think that our passion, motivation, and effort all show in the animation.
絶対 映像に表れると思う
だから自分のこと
信じて大丈夫だよ
So you should try to believe in yourself more.
You'll be just fine.
（ミムジー）
うんしょ！
Don't do that. You need to dry your hair properly or you'll catch a cold.
（ロロ）
ダメだよ
ちゃんと髪の毛 乾かさないと
風邪ひいちゃうよ
Hey!
ねえってば
な～に モチャモチャ
考え事してんだろね？
What's gotten her all broody today?
It must be today's fight.
あれかな？　今日のケンカ
Mistress Okitsu is really something!
あ～ さすが興津女史だよね
That's true, but it's besides the point.
それはそうだけど
そうじゃなくて
Let them fight all they want.
They'll get bored of it eventually.
ケンカなんて好きにやらせとけば
そのうち飽きたらやめるっしょ
That's anarchy.
それじゃあ無法地帯だよ
Dai-chan, good morning!
（太郎）
大ちゃん おはよ～う！
俺たちはバディだよ バディ
We're buddies! You know! Buddies!
What's wrong with you?
なんだよ
Got it? It means partner!
分かる？　相棒って意味
We're not partners.
相棒じゃねえし
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
About that...
そのことなんですけど
3rd Girls' Fighter Wing
Yamada-san and Madoka-san will be working on episode 12's storyboards together.
12話の絵コンテは
山田さんと円さんの
お二人で
描いてもらうことになりました
That means you two should oversee it together.
これは高梨さんと平岡さん
２人で担当してください
It was all, bang! Boom!
もうね
バ～ン！　ドカ～ン！　って
（葛城）ひゃ～
（舞茸）熱いね～
Sounds pretty intense. But then they dialed it down a notch and settled in, right?
でも雨降って地固まったんだろ？
はい まあ…
You could say that.
I'd rather not have any more trouble though.
もう これ以上のトラブルは
ごめんだよ
女子校だと
つかみ合いとかしないの？
Do you have quarrels in all-girls schools?
Or like, really rough cat fights?
逆に激しいキャットファイトとか
あるんじゃないの？
Not at all!
ないです ないです
No falling-outs?
（舞茸）
仲たがいとかもしない？
Sure, tensions rise from time to time.
ちょっと怪しくなることなら
But afterwards, both sides act like the fight never happened
でもケンカしても ケンカしたと
お互い認めないようにして
and start repairing the relationship.
うま～く関係修復に
もってく感じです
Sounds like some serious people skills.
（舞茸）
対人スキル高いな～
"Want a steamed bun?" "Sure."
“蒸しパン食べる？”
“うん”くらいですかね
That's about it.
Make that donuts.
That's the symbol of making up.
いや そこはドーナツで
それが仲直りの合図
リアル世界で そのメタファー
高度すぎだろ
I can't say if that metaphor actually works in real world.
Which reminds me,
あっ そういや12話で
ありあがキャシーに
in episode 12, Cathy asks Aria what she'll do once the war is over.
“戦いが終わったらどうするの？”
って聞かれて…
Once the war is over and the world's back to normal,
（キャサリン）
この戦いが終わって
世界が元に戻ったら
I'm totally going back to Texas!
私 絶対テキサスに戻らなきゃ
I'd like to attend the Conservatoire once again.
（クリスティーネ）
私は もう一度
コンセルバトワールに通いたいわ
It won't be easy to fix my body though.
体を元に戻すのが
大変そうだけど
I want to go and see my grandma!
（タチアナ）
タチアナは
おばあちゃんに会いたいです
Ah, the borscht and kasha she makes!
おばあちゃんの作った
ボルシチ カーシャ ああ…
Is your grandmother in good health?
（ノア）
おばあさまは息災なのか？
She's fine! I'm sure she's fine!
（無線:タチアナ）
大丈夫です　きっと大丈夫だと
タチアナは信じています
I see.
そうか　お前の家族なら
しぶとそうだしな
I figured your family would be pretty resilient too.
What are you gonna do?
（タチアナ）
そういう自分は何すんですか？
I'll go work at a Dead Sea spa.
（ノア）
私は死海エステだ
あの浮かぶやつですか？
The one you float on?
いいわね～ 羨ましいわ
Sounds nice. I'm jealous.
What will you do when the war's over, Aria?
ありあは この戦いが
終わったら どうするの？
There's something you want to do, right?
（無線:キャサリン）
やりたいことあるでしょ？
別に
Not really.
Nothing at all? No way!
何もないの？　ウソでしょ？
Then what are you fighting for?
じゃあ
なんのために戦ってるわけ？
That's so like you though.
でも なんか ありあっぽい
キャシーにとっては夢と未来に
関する問いだったかもしれない
Cathy was asking about her dreams and the future.
But it pierced Aria.
でも ありあには突き刺さった
あっ そうか！
ありあは きっとキャシーに
I see! Aria must've thought Cathy meant it like,
"Why are you fighting? There's no point in it!"
“なんで戦ってんの？
戦う意味ないじゃん”
…みたいに言われたと思ったんだ
えっ？
ありあは そんなにやわい？
Is Aria that sensitive?
Maybe in episode one, but we're talking about
それは１話だったらともかく
the girl who even ate Cathy's terribly overcooked spinach without a single complaint.
キャシーがゆでた
グズグズのホウレンソウを
我慢して食べたありあですから
I think she was hurt by Cathy's words
ありあは
キャシーの言葉に傷ついて
and shocked by the fact that she got hurt at all.
自分が傷ついたことに
ショックを受けたんだと思います
The Ice Doll is melting.
アイスドールが揺らいでる
That's why she can't fly.
だから飛べなくなった
I...
私は… 降りる
quit.
…であれば ありあの気持ちを
キャシーが理解した時
So then, when Cathy figures out how Aria feels,
what would she say to reassure her?
どんな話をすれば ありあの
わだかまりは ほどける？
What would Cathy say? And Aria's response?
キャシーはなんて言う？
ありあは？
Maitake-san, do we need that in episode 13?
舞茸さん そのシチュエーション
13話に入れます？
Isn't it a bit too straightforward the way it is now?
あっ… だって今の流れだと
ストレートすぎません？
"My friends are getting cornered.
I've gotta help them!" That's just...
“戦ってる仲間がピンチだから
助けなきゃ”で出ていくとか
王道じゃないですか
But it's tried and true, right?
王道も悪くないけど
これは「サンジョ」だよ
It is, but this is 3rd Wing.
We should go further.
もうちょっと
なんとかしましょうよ
Agreed!
賛成！
できればセリフのやりとりじゃなく
If possible, use their facial expressions instead of words!
表情芝居で希望！
Doing it with no dialogue is a bit much.
セリフなしは さすがに厳しいな
Make it short and sweet!
（木下）端的に短く
（舞茸）う～ん
Dr. Diesel, try writing the lines for this scene.
はい ディーゼルさん
この時の会話 書いてみて
Maitake-san...
舞茸さん…
It'd sound too artificial if I did it.
僕が書くと なんか堅苦しい会話に
なっちゃいそうでさ
Of course, I'll revise it later.
もちろん
僕が後でリライトするけど
やります！
I'll do it!
The first draft for the 3rd Wing final episode is done.
「サンジョ」最終話
初稿 上がりました
I don't feel entitled just because I'm a girl,
and I'm not taking this lightly.
女だからいいとは思ってないし
仕事もナメてません
Whatever.
知らねえよ
実際 私が考えたセリフ
１行も採用されなかったし
None of the lines I wrote were used in the end.
When spring comes, let's go and find newborn calves.
春になったら
一緒に生まれたばかりの子牛を
探しに行こうよ
The mother cow stays in one place with them, so they're easy to spot.
母牛が近くでじっとしてるから
すぐに分かるの
The newborns are slimy and shaky.
生まれたての子牛って
じっとり湿っててグンニャリしてる
First we clear the mouths and noses
最初に鼻や口をふいて
and make sure there's no
amniotic fluid or amnion left.
羊水や羊膜が残ってないか確かめる
（ひび割れる音）
They stand up right away.
大丈夫 すぐに立つから
If you spot a baby calf straying from the group,
wrap it tightly in a blanket.
もし はぐれた子牛がいたら
すぐに毛布で くるんであげる
They calm down if you hug them, you see.
きつめにね
ハグされてると落ち着くんだって
It's okay. I'll be fine.
大丈夫 私は大丈夫
So promise me, Aria...
だから約束して ありあ
一緒に子牛を見つけに行くって
that we'll go together to find newborn calves.
I don't...
私には…
I don't have anything I want to do.
（あおい）
“やりたいことなんてない”
I don't know if I'll ever find anything like that either.
“これから見つけられるか
どうかも分からない”
But if you all have your own dreams...
“でも みんなが
やりたいことがあるなら”
the least I can do...
“それを 援護することはできる”
is support you.
This is Musani.
The PM, Miyamori?
She's kinda... I mean, kind of busy right now!
Next time on Shirobako: "Don't Take Quality Hostage!"
Don't Take Quality Hostage!
（みどり）
はい ムサニです
デスクの宮森ですか？
あ～ 今取り込み中みたいっす
じゃない… です！
次回
「ＳＨＩＲＯＢＡＫＯ(シロバコ)」